# Frank Wood

21 Claremont Ave. Apt. 93 New York, NY 10027, USA Phone: +16467172202 fwood@stat.columbia.edu Department of Statistics Columbia University 1255 Amsterdam Ave. New York, NY 10027, USA

http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~fwood

## RESEARCH OVERVIEW

My primary research area is applied statistical machine learning. My research interests range from the development of new probabilistic models and inference algorithms to real-world applications. My research contributions include new models and inference algorithms as well as novel applications of such models to problems in compression, neuroscience, robotics, and natural language processing.

#### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D., Computer Science, 2007

"Nonparametric Bayesian Models for Neural Data"

Advisor: Prof. Michael J. Black Brown University, Providence, RI

M.S., Computer Science, 2004 Advisor: Prof. Michael J. Black Brown University, Providence, RI

B.S., Computer Science, 1996 Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

#### Positions

Assistant Professor New York, NY

Founder
Zurich, CH

Postdoctoral Fellow London, UK Columbia University 2009 – present

Betacular, Ltd.

2010 – present

Gatsby Unit, UCL 2007 – 2009

Consultant Stan James Limited
Gibraltar 2008 – 2009

Stan James is a sports bookmaker. Initiated the development of mathematically consistent market pricing tools and introduced statistical market prediction methods.

Chief Executive Officer

Interfolio, Inc.

Washington, DC

2002

Interfolio is an online academic credential file management provider. Tripled revenue, doubled partner schools and user base, acquired ReferenceNow, LLC (a competitor), and negotiated contracts for debt reduction and strategic partnerships.

Principal Engineer

AOL Time Warner

Dulles, VA

2000 - 2001

Designed (then) the world's largest production image and mp3 search engines. Filed 5 patents for image, mp3, and text search innovations. Managed multimedia search engineering team.

Chief Executive Officer / Founder

Washington, DC

ToFish!, Inc. 1998 - 2000

ToFish! was a content-based image search technology company. Negotiated sale of company to AOL for a 400%+ return on investment. Managed marketing, sales, legal, finance, and technical teams. Arranged "friends and family" and early state venture financing. Negotiated contracts for sales, intellectual property, and employment.

Research Engineer

Lawrence Berkeley **National Laboratory** 

Berkeley, CA and Washington, DC

1997 - 1998

Contributed to successful grant proposals for over \$500,000. Communicated laboratory research to congressional staff. Designed and implemented virtual reality simulations.

Research Engineer

Cornell Theory Center

Ithaca, NY

1996 - 1997

Designed and implemented the first virtual reality "window manager." Implemented a military in-flight re-fueling simulator. Investigated novel super-computing computational steering algorithms.

Teaching EXPERIENCE Instructor

Columbia University

Fall 2010 -

New York, NY

Course title: "Data Mining/Statistical Machine Learning."

Instructor

Columbia University

New York, NY

Fall 2009 -

Course title: "Linear Regression Models."

Guest Lecturer

**Princeton University** 

Princeton, NJ

**April 2009** 

Course title: "Foundations of Probabilistic Modeling."

Guest Lecturer

Columbia University

New York, NY

March 2009

Course title: "Statistical analysis of neural data."

Guest Lecturer

University College London

London, UK

January 2008

Course title: "Advanced Topics in Machine Learning."

Teaching Assistant

**Brown University** 

Providence, RI

January 2005 – June 2005

Course title: "Topics in brain computer interfaces."

Advising

J. Huggins, BS, Computer Science, Columbia University,

W. Neiswanger, BS, Applied Math, Columbia University,

N.Bartlett, MSc, Statistics, Columbia University,

J. Gasthaus, MSc, University College London, Spike Sorting using Time-Varying Dirichlet Process Mixture Models, 2009

PATENTS

M. J. Black, W. Wu, and F. Wood, 11,086,956, Method and system for automatic decoding of motor cortical activity, 2005

G. Pass and F. Wood, 6,671,402, Representing an image with weighted joint histogram, 2003

G. Pass and F. Wood, 6,522,782, Image and text searching techniques, 2003

G. Pass and F. Wood, 6,556,710, Image searching techniques, 2003

G. Pass and F. Wood, 6,622,780, Indexing of images and/or text, 2003

G. Pass and F. Wood, 6,522,779, Representing an image with a posterized joint histogram, 2003

Awards and

IMSA Alumni Distinguished Leadership Award 2011

Honors

AISTATS Best Paper Award 2009

National Science Foundation Research Experience for Undergraduates, Cornell Theory

Center, 1994

Honors College Scholar, University of Illinois at Chicago, 1992

SERVICE

NIPS Area Chair, 2011

IJCAI Senior Program Committee, 2010 AISTATS Senior Program Committee, 2010

Columbia University Statistics Department Computing Committee, 2009

Gatsby external talks coordinator, 2008-2009

Support

Google research award \$70,000, 2010

Xerox faculty research award \$90,000, 2011

# Frank Wood

### Journal Publications

- F. Wood, J. Gasthaus, C. Archambeau, L. James, and Y.W. Teh. The sequence memoizer. *Communications of the ACM*, 54(2):91–98, 2011.
- F. Wood and M. J. Black. A non-parametric Bayesian alternative to spike sorting. *Journal of Neuroscience Methods*, 173:1–12, 2008.
- D. H. Grollman, O. C. Jenkins, and F. Wood. Discovering natural kinds of robot sensory experiences in unstructured environments. *Journal of Field Robotics*, 23:1077–1089, 2006.
- F. Wood, M. Fellows, C. Vargas-Irwin, M. J. Black, and J. P. Donoghue. On the variability of manual spike sorting. *IEEE Transactions in Biomedical Engineering*, 51:912–918, 2004.
- F. Wood, D. Brown, B. Amidon, J. Alferness, B. Joseph, R. E. Gillilan, and C. Faerman. Windowing and telecollaboration for virtual reality with applications to the study of a tropical disease. *IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications*, 16:72–78, 1996.
- R. E. Gillilan and F. Wood. Visualization, virtual reality, and animation within the data flow model of computing. *Computer Graphics*, 29:55–58, 1995.

# REFEREED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

- A. Perotte, N. Bartlett Noiemie Elhadad, and F. Wood. Hierarchically supervised latent Dirichlet allocation. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems*, to appear, 2012.
- N. Bartlett and F. Wood. Deplump for streaming data. In *Data Compression Conference*, pages 363–372, 2011.
- D. Pfau, N. Bartlett, and F. Wood. Probabilistic deterministic infinite automata. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems*, pages 1930–1938, 2011.
- N. Bartlett, D. Pfau, and F. Wood. Forgetting counts: Constant memory inference for a dependent hierarchical Pitman-Yor process. In *Proceedings of the 26th International Conference on Machine Learning*, pages 63–70, 2010.
- J. Gasthaus, F. Wood, and Y.W. Teh. Lossless compression based on the Sequence Memoizer. In *Data Compression Conference*, pages 337–345, 2010.
- F. Wood, C. Archambeau, J. Gasthaus, L. James, and Y.W. Teh. A stochastic memoizer for sequence data. In *Proceedings of the 26th International Conference on Machine Learning*, pages 1129–1136, 2009.
- F. Wood and Y.W. Teh. A hierarchical nonparametric Bayesian approach to statistical language model domain adaptation. In *Artificial Intelligence and Statistics*, pages 607–614, 2009.
- J. Gasthaus, F. Wood, D. Görür, and Y.W. Teh. Dependent Dirichlet process spike sorting. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems*, pages 497–504, 2009.
- P. Berkes, J.W. Pillow, and F. Wood. Characterizing neural dependencies with Poisson copula models. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems*, pages  $129-136,\,2009$ .
- F. Wood and T. L. Griffiths. Particle filtering for non-parametric Bayesian matrix factorization. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems*, pages 1513–1520, 2006.

- F. Wood, S. Goldwater, and M. J. Black. A non-parametric Bayesian approach to spike sorting. In *Proceedings of the 28th IEEE Conference on Engineering in Medicine and Biological Systems*, pages 1165–1169, 2006.
- F. Wood, T. L. Griffiths, and Z. Ghahramani. A non-parametric Bayesian method for inferring hidden causes. In *Proceedings of the 22nd Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence*, pages 536–543, 2006.
- S. P. Kim, F. Wood, and M. J. Black. Statistical analysis of the non-stationarity of neural population codes. In *The First IEEE / RAS-EMBS International Conference on Biomedical Robotics and Biomechatronics*, pages 259–299, 2006.
- F. Wood, S. Roth, and M. J. Black. Modeling neural population spiking activity with Gibbs distributions. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems*, pages 1537–1544, 2005.
- F. Wood, Prabhat, J. P. Donoghue, and M. J. Black. Inferring attentional state and kinematics from motor cortical firing rates. In *Proceedings of the 27th IEEE Conference on Engineering in Medicine and Biological Systems*, pages 149–152, 2005.
- F. Wood, M. Fellows, J. P. Donoghue, and M. J. Black. Automatic spike sorting for neural decoding. In *Proceedings of the 27th IEEE Conference on Engineering in Medicine and Biological Systems*, pages 4126–4129, 2004.

### TECHNICAL REPORTS

F. Wood, D.H. Grollman, K.A. Heller, O.C. Jenkins, and M.J. Black. Incremental nonparametric Bayesian regression. Technical Report CS-08-07, Brown University, Department of Computer Science, 2008.

## Workshop Publications

- F. Wood and Y.W. Teh. A hierarchical, hierarchical Pitman Yor process language model. In *ICML/UAI Nonparametric Bayes Workshop*, 2008.
- D. H. Grollman, O. C. Jenkins, and F. Wood. Discovering natural kinds of robot sensory experiences in unstructured environments. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems Workshop on Machine Learning Based Robotics in Unstructured Environments*, 2005.

#### Abstracts

- F. Wood and M. J. Black, Energy Based Models of Motor Cortical Population Activity, *Society for Neuroscience*, Washington, DC 2005
- F. Wood, M. Fellows, J. P. Donoghue, and M. J. Black, Automatic Spike Sorting for Neural Decoding, *Statistical Analysis of Neural Data*, Pittsburg, PA 2004
- F. Wood, M. Fellows, M. J. Black, and J. P. Donoghue, Accuracy of manual spike sorting: results for the Utah intracortical array, *Society for Neuroscience*, New Orleans, LA 2003

Reviewing Neural Information Processing Systems

> Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence Artificial Intelligence and Statistics

International Conference on Machine Learning

Journal of Machine Learning Research

Association for the Advancement of Artificial Intelligence

Journal of Neuroscience Methods

IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering

IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence

International Joint Conferences on Artificial Intelligence

Journal of Statistics and Computing

"Applied Virtual Reality", SigGraph, Course 14, Los Angeles, CA, 1997 Invited

Conference "The Sequence Memoizer", Information Theory and Applications Workshop, UCSD,

Presentations 2011

INVITED TALKS "The Sequence Memoizer"

Columbia University, Brown University, University of Edinburgh, Oxford University,

Australia National University 2009

"Nonparametric Bayesian Natural Language Model Domain Adaptation"

Columbia University, Princeton University, University of Utah 2009

"Nonparametric Bayesian Natural Language Model Domain Adaptation"

Radboud University, NL and Cambridge University, UK 2007 "A Nonparametric Bayesian Alternative to Spike Sorting"

University College London, UK and Radboud University, NL 2007

"Gentle Introduction to Infinite Gaussian Mixture Modeling"

Brown University, RI, 2006

"Bayesian Decoding for Neural Prostheses"

Northwestern University, IL, 2005

"Variability of Manual Spike Sorting for Multi-Electrode Arrays"

University of Chicago, IL, 2003